Guide to the The Bradley Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bradley family papers
1817-1950
MS 777
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, notebooks, account books, photographs, memorabilia, and other papers of the Bradley family of New Haven, Connecticut. The papers, which are largely from the 19th century, include Civil War letters, account books by a New Haven manufacturer, and a photograph album. There are also World War I letters from Edward H. Bradley.
Bradley family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Bradley family, 1941-1942
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
The Bradley Family Papers consist of correspondence, journals, account books, notebooks, school notes, writings, deeds and other miscellaneous items of the Bradley family of New Haven, Connecticut.
The Bradley faimly settled in New Haven at the beginning of the 17th century. The papers span the years 1795 to 1950, but the heaviest concentration of material covers the years 1814 to 1870.
While the papers touch on New Haven history (19th century), the Civil War and World War I, they are not substantive enough to allow a thorough development of any of these subjects. The papers contain materials from the following individuals:
William C. Bradley (1821-1890) The papers of William Bradley, a New Haven merchant, who manufactured carriage springs and sold scrap iron, contain two account books, a waste book, two notebooks and one journal, all relating to his business.
George Bradley (c. 1840-?) George Bradley, a soldier during the Civil War, stationed in Virginia, fought in the battle of Fredericksburg and was taken prisoner during the battle of Chancellorsville. The letters he wrote home from the battle field and later while a prisoner of war are an interesting segment of these papers. This correspondence is dated 1862 to 1863.
Edward Elias Bradley (1845-1939) Edward E. Bradley, the youngest son of Isaac and Abigail Bradley, began his career as a shipping clerk with the New Haven Wheel Company in 1860 and rose to the presidency of the company by 1887. During the Civil War, he was captain of the Company F-2nd Regiment. Bradley's other occupations included paymaster general of Connecticut, member of the Connecticut House of Representatives (1882-1883) and Senate(1886), and president of the State Park Association (1930). Bradley also served as Adjunct General of Connecticut from 1893 to 1895. There is a photograph album from this period, which contains photographs of Bradley and the Governor's staff.
Included in the papers are three original manuscripts by Edward Elias Bradley. The subjects of these papers are General Israel Putnam, Connecticut Revolutionary War hero, Timothy Dwight, president of Yale (1795-1817), and the erection of the Defenders Monument in New Haven.
Edward Holbrook Bradley (1897-?) Edward H. Bradley left Yale College in his sophomore year(1917) to join the American Ambulance Corps that was stationed in France during World War I. After arriving in France, Bradley discovered that there was a shortage of drivers in the Convois Automobile Service of the French Army. He spent 1917 in the service of the French Army, driving a camion that carried ammunition and supplies to the frount lines. A type script of some of the letters he wrote home during this period gives some description of life in France during the war. Bradley returned to Yale after the war and graduated in 1920.
The Bradley Family Papers also contain material from other family members but this represents only a small portion of the collection.
Biographical / Historical
William C. Bradley (1821-1890): manufacturer of carriage springs in New Haven, Connecticut. George Bradley (b. ca. 1840): soldier in the Civil War. Edward Elias Bradley (1845-1938): active in Connecticut politics. Edward Holbrook Bradley (1897-1968): broker in New Haven, Connecticut
Business; Families; Fredericksburg, Battle of, Fredericksburg, Va., 1862; World War, 1914-1918; Connecticut -- Politics and government; New Haven (Conn.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Account books; Deeds; Manufacturers; Bradley, Edward Elias, 1845-1938; Bradley, Edward Holbrook, 1897-1968; Bradley, George, ca. 1840-; Bradley, William C., 1821-1890; Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817; Putnam, Israel, 1718-1790; Bradley family
- Inventory
  - Bradley, Horace
    - Ledger, 1817-1844 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bradley, Stephan
    - Correspondence, 1818 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bradley, William C.
    - Correspondence, 1851 August 6, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bradley, Bertha
    - Report card from Day School for Young Ladies and Girls, New Haven Connecticut, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bradley, William
    - Waste book, 1827-1836 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Book of accounts, vol. I, 1827-1841 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Book of accounts, vol. II, 1831- 1838 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Journal, Circa1830 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bradley, Charles William
    - Notebook, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes, memoranda and fragments, Circa 1840 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Deeds, Connecticut, 1858 April 3-1866 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bradley, George H.
    - Civil War correspondence, 1862 January 21-1863 July 17 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bradley, Edward Elias
    - Governors staff photograph album, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "General Israel Putnam, " autograph manuscript, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 12 - 13)
    - "History of Defenders Monument Project", 1911 October 27 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Timothy Dwight, Chaplain of American Army", 1913 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Timothy Dwight, Chaplain of American Army," unfinished autograph manuscript, 1913 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Timothy Dwight, Chaplain of American Army," typewritten manuscript.
    - Introduction, 1913 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Timothy Dwight, Chaplain of American Army," typewritten manuscript, 1913 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bradley, Edward Holbrook
    - Extracts from letters written while serving in Convois Automobile Service of the French Army, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bradley, Edward M.
    - Obituary, 1950 February 15 (Box 3, Folder 19)